本作品由 腾    蛟 荣誉出品
下载后仅供学习交流,严禁用于商业途径
一九一二年二月十二日
Feb. 12, 1912
压制:  腾    蛟   双显&特效字幕: 腾    蛟
武昌起义第二年
second year of the Revolution.
清廷隆裕皇太后终于被迫颁蚜虽咭
An edict proclaimed
退位诏书
the abdication of Emperor Pu Yi.
从此结束
And the end of
统治中国近三百年历史的清皇朝
the Manchu Dynasty.
为中国人带来了新希望
A new China was in the offing.
但是也有很多人
Many,
成为大时代变迁的牺牲品
太监，就是其中一种人
Eunuchs, for instance.
外表上太监的品级及职务繁复
Grand their titles might be.
实质也不外的皇族身边的奴隶
They were in fact royal slaves.
所有太监都要净身
Castration is the eunuch's prerequisite.
就是把男性生殖器官阉割
That means the removal of male genitals.
按历代太监的惯例
The eunuchs down the centuries
净身后阉割下来的器官称为宝贝
called fondly the cut off part as Pet.
首先用油炸透，再用油纸包妥
The Pet was boiled in oil and wrapped
放在秤量食的升内，吊在屋梁之上
put in a container and suspended in midair
也只有贫苦家庭的子弟，为生活所迫
The eunuchs invariably came from poor families.
而踏上这条无法翩身的悲惨道路
They were forced onto this path of no return.
一、二，一、二…
One, two, one, two...
快点，快点
Hurry up.
等等我，等等我
Wait for me.
来喜    是
- Laishi. - Yes.
是，总管
Yes, Master Eunuch.
你替我摘朵花来    是
- Get me that flower. - Yes.
快点，快点
Hurry up.
真没用，快点拿过来
Hurry up, you stupid.
追他    是
- Get him. - Yes.
招弟
Tsouti.
拿着
Take it.
小德张回来了
Young Teh Chang is here.
来喜，过来，快点
Laishi, come over here.
是什么人呀？
Who's that?
是小德张    小德张？
- It's Young Teh Chang - Young Teh Chang?
有骨的不要拿呀
Don't take those with bones.
好味道，好味道
Yummy, yummy.
不要这样子，乡下的小孩真可怜
Don't, these kids are so pitiful.
不要丢在地上，折坠呀
Don't dump it on the ground.
是，是很可怜，张公公说得对
Lord Chang is right, they are pitiable.
放在桶里给他们吃吧
Leave it in the barrel for them.
我们走吧
Let's go.
走，走
Go, go.
那里还有一桶呀
One more barrel there.
阿爹
Dad.
再见
Bye.
早知道割掉小祖宗去服侍皇帝
The emperor is easier
比服侍一个女人好
to please than she is.
我也割掉
I want to have my thing snipped.
割你的头
Nonsense.
我割了去服侍皇帝
I want to serve
那就可以跟小德张一样
the emperor.
有鞋子穿，有轿子坐
Then I'd have shoes to wear.
阿爹，有鸡尾巴吧呀
It's a chicken bottom.
真是鸡尾巴呀，先嗅一下
Really? Let me have a sniff.
我分两份
I'll split it in two.
不用了，我吃过了，你吃吧
No need, you have it all.
等一等，你什么时候替我割呀？
When can I have my thing snipped?
问你妈妈吧
Ask your mother.
你妈妈答应的话，我就肯
If she says yes, then it's alright.
去吧，去吧
Go, go.
真的？
Really?
真的
Yes.
真的？
Really?
是呀
Yes.
祥福
Chiang Fu.
三爷，这么早呀
Good morning, sir.
我今天来不是要你交田租
I'm not here for the rent.
不过有件事要你帮忙
I'm here for a favour.
你想死吗？    不要打我
- Are you crazy? - Don't hit me.
你饿到发昏了    我不敢了
- You are out of your mind. - I wouldn't dare anymore.
你走吧，你走了就不要回来
Get lost and don't come back.
你说，你做好人，我们吃什么呀？
You did him a favour, what about us?
三爷说…
But
三爷说一句
he said...
你就把米缸的米全部给了他
And you had to offer him all our food.
我们怎能过年呀？你说
How do we carry on?
三爷说皇上有麻烦
He said the emperor's in trouble.
我们的困难有谁会理呢？你说吧
We're in trouble too, and who cares?
我回去妈妈那里
I'm going,
你叫皇帝请你吃龙肉吧
you go to your emperor.
皇帝没有饭吃
The emperor protects us from foreigners.
谁去打红毛鬼，谁去打山贼呀？
And the revolutionaries.
谁去打革命党？
Who'll take care of us
饿死了皇帝，谁去理我们呀？
if the emperor's dead?
好呀，好呀
Great, great.
过来
Come here.
走
Go.
来喜妈，不要走吧
Don't go.
没有人烧饭给我吃，我会饿死的
Who's going to cook for us?
烧，用什么烧呀？
Cooking with what?
我去掘些菜头回来
I'm going to dig up some roots.
掘菜头？
Dig up some roots?
来喜，来
Come here, Laishi.
来什么？
What for?
吃了半年菜根糊
Mesh roots again?
吃到每个人变为菜根了，你还要吃？
Aren't you tired of it yet?
你不走了？
Aren't you going?
我去借几两米糠，暂时顶住肚皮
I'm going to borrow some rice.
好了，我们有米糠吃了
Great, rice for dinner.
阿爹，不行了
Mum's here
妈妈在这里我岂不是不可以割
can't do it now.
岂不是没有鸡尾巴吃了
No more chicken bottoms.
那怎么办？    赶走妈妈吧
- What now? - Send her away.
阿爹，你不想吃鸡尾巴吗？
Don't you want some chicken bottoms?
你想办法吧
Think of something.
你为什么掷我？
Why are you throwing things at me?
阿爹，你真好胆
How dare you.
我去借量，你就觉得没面子
You feel ashamed that I'm borrowing.
阿爹，赶走妈妈，赶走妈妈吧
Send her away, dad.
我是个男人
I'm a man.
就算饿死了也不用你乞回来给我吃
I won't beg for food.
你滚
Get away.
跟我走
Come with me.
来喜
Laishi.
我也是个男子汉
I'm a man too.
好
Good.
阿爹
Dad.
阿爹，你去那里呀？
Dad, where are you going?
我去找你妈妈
To find your mother.
你帮我割掉后才找妈妈吧
Snip it off before you do that.
阿爹，你先坐下
Sit down, dad.
阿爹，我割掉后就不用再捱饿了
Everything's alright after I snip it off.
妈妈就不会再骂你了
Mum won't be mad at you again.
阿爹，我是个男子汉，要第一个割
Dad, I'm a man, I'll be the first.
照顾妹妹
Take care of your sister.
地保，地保
District Chief.
城里发生什么事了？
What happened in town?
好消息，大清皇帝打败仗
Good news, the emperor is out.
现在革命党作主
The revolutionaries won.
是吗？
Is that right?
又不知道谁做皇帝了
Who'll be the new emperor?
不知道，我只知道要把辫子剪掉
Don't know. But no more pig-tails for sure.
阿爹，是什么呀？
What's there, dad?
白蜡、鹅毛、石灰炒、花椒粉
Wax, goose down, calcium powder, chili.
有什么用的？
What for?
以前听你的爷爷说，是用来止血的
To stop bleeding, according to grandpa.
要割多少呀？
To snip off how much?
你有多少就割多少
Whatever is there.
将来跟你的妹妹一样
You'll be just like your sister.
我叫你去找的东西呢？
Have you got what I told you to get?
这件怎么办？
What's that?
斩头吗？
For chopping off heads?
不剪辫会不会杀头呀？
Death penalty for keeping a pig-tail?
执政的说杀就杀，不杀就不杀
Up to the Government.
那是杀还是不杀呀？
So is it the death penalty or not?
执政的没有吩咐嘛
No one mentioned anything yet.
好厉害呀
It's bloody sharp.
来了
Ready.
好
Yes.
我割了
I'm going to do it.
来吧
Come on.
我真的割了
For real now.
不可以，不可以
No, no way.
剪了还是个人吗？
It's like castration.
有没有说谁是皇帝呀？    没有
- Who's going to be emperor? - Don't know.
来吧
Come on.
妈妈，妈妈
Mum, mum.
妈妈，我是不是第一个割呀？
Mum, am I the first one?
妈妈，我很痛，我尿急呀
It hurts, mum. I want to pee.
不要动，不要动，伤口还没痊愈
Don't move, it hasn't healed yet.
六婶说要睡足一百天才可以下床
You must sleep for 100 days.
乖
Good boy.
很急呀，我要屙尿
I want to pee.
不痛，不痛，屙完要换一条新鹅毛管
Must change a new feather after peeling.
六婶说要天天更换的
Must change everyday.
乖，不留下个洞
Or else you have to
将来尿会从鼻孔出来的
pee with your nose.
乖
Good boy.
我问到了
I have the answer.
问到了？
Yes?
要用油炸，九叔说炸完吹干用布扎实
Must fry in oil, and wrap after dry.
我借了四两油
I've borrowed some oil.
那你还不去炸？
So go ahead.
我还要替他换药
I have to change the medicine.
来喜割掉出来的宝贝呢？
Where's the thing?
在汤碗里
In the bowl.
还等什么？
What are you waiting for?
我忘了问九叔
I've forgot to
要不要用姜葱先爆香镬子
get the recipe.
就这样子炸吧，记住要火大一点
Never mind, use a large fire.
孩子挂一辈子
He has to keep it for lift.
炸得不够透会发霉的
Has to be well done.
很晚了，其实也没有什么好看的
It's late, go home please.
天气这么冷很容易着凉的，回家吧
Go home, weather's getting cold.
走吧，走吧
Go now.
你小心着凉呀
Don't catch cold.
你的儿子做了清朝最后一个太监了
Your son is the last eunuch of Ching Dynasty.
来喜大总管，来喜大太监，出来吧
Come out, Laishi, Master Eunuch.
来你的仆街，再叫没好死
Shut up you scum. Shut up.
再叫生仔没屁股，再叫吊颈死
Or you'll be cursed.
宝贝呢？
Where's the thing?
带来了，在包袱里
It's in the bag.
九叔说
Keep it
百年归老要将它放在你的棺材里
even into the coffin with you.
不然将来投胎就不可以再做人了
Or you won't be a man in the next life.
记得吗？
Do you remember?
记得了
Yes.
不可以失掉的
Don't lose it.
我将来要坐轿回来
I shall return in a sedan.
到时一定会请你们吃鸡尾巴的
And there'll be a lot of chicken bottoms.
乖
Good boy.
走吧
Go.
我们走了
We are going.
阿爹，有没有像我年纪那么小
Any Masters of my age, dad?
就做大总管的？
The emperor
现在总统不准皇帝用太监了
doesn't need eunuchs anymore.
你放心，我想皇帝很快就会打赢总统
The emperor will win back his throne soon.
那你就可能做太监了
Then you'll be a eunuch.
那是什么时候？
When?
你在城里二老爷的戏班先学一些东西
You must try to learn from
我想很快的
the troupe.
行了
Alright.
停
Stop.
来喜
Laishi.
现在叫你扮杨贵妃喝醉酒
You're supposed to
不是叫你扮胭脂胡同的醉鸡
be a drunken empress.
发花癫，四处走
Not a prostitute on the loose.
杨贵妃风情万种，说话莺声燕语
An empress speaks elegantly.
喝醉酒时走起路也像摇风摆柳
Sways like a willow when drunk.
不像你这样子难看
Not clumsy like you.
唐明皇要是叫鸡
Who wants
也不喜欢你这个杨贵妃了
an emperor like you?
走开，我再做一次给你看
Let me show you.
贵妃醉酒就是你师父我当年拿手好戏
It was my favourite role.
如果不是你师父突然间肥了
I'd do it myself
也不会轮到你去做
if I were slimmer.
就好像她喝醉了出花园的一段
Take this drunken scene.
真舒服
Feel good.
是什么呢？
What's that?
真芳香
Smell so good.
原来是一朵花
Oh? A flower.
我要摘了它下来，拿在手里
Let me put it
插在头上
in my hair.
一定会很漂亮的
Must be pretty.
让我走近看清楚
I'll take a closer look.
真芳香
Smell so good.
看看这朵是什么花？
What kind of a flower?
你们看见没有？    看见了
- Got it. - Yes.
还不扶我起来？
Then come pick me up.
好
Good.
先吃点东西吧，大帅
Have a bite, General.
自己吃自己吧
Eat it yourself.
好
Good.
明天散戏后带他回来见我
Bring him to me tomorrow.
是
Yes.
师父
Master.
二老板
Boss.
师父，坐吧
Have a seat, master.
今天的观众反应不错    是吗？
- Good response - Really?
不过不要先开心，不一定是赞你的
Not necessary for you.
知道了
Yes.
有人回静海去
Anything for your folks.
有没有东西带返乡下呀？
Someone's going that way.
有呀，有呀
Yes, there is.
三、四、五、六
3, 4, 5, 6.
我只教你上台唱戏
Are you on the run or what?
我有教你走难的吗？
Will you ask the person to take these?
师父，麻烦你帮我托人送返乡下吧
可以
Alright.
不买新衣服的话也得买双新鞋子
At least get a new pair of shoes.
不是呀，旧鞋很舒服的
I like the old ones.
明天到天桥那里去买双鞋子吧
Go get a new pair tomorrow.
谢谢师父
Thank you, master.
师父，替我带返乡下吧
Take this to my folks please.
叫你去买就买好了
Go buy the shoes.
不用了，下个月出量才买吧
I buy a pair when I get paid.
鞋子还可以穿
The old ones are still good.
不买就省掉
Never mind then.
师父，师父
Master, master.
什么？想拿回？
What? Want it back?
不是，那件事怎么样？
No. Any news?
你跟了我多少年？
How long have you been with me?
九年
9 years.
不，十年了
No, more like 10.
现在没有饭你吃，没有衣服你穿
Aren't you well fed and well treated?
没教足你的功夫吗？
Haven't I taught you everything?
不是，不是
Yes, yes.
不过现在外面很混乱，没有人负责
But it's chao outside.
宣统皇帝才是真命天子
The emperor is our true leader.
他需要人来服侍
He needs to be served.
师父不要人服侍吗？
Don't I need to be served?
要，要
Of course.
不过…
But?
师父，你先过来这边，来吧
Please come over here.
我是公公，公公就要入宫
I'm a eunuch, eunuchs stay in the Palace.
公公不用吃饭和大小便吗？
What's so special about being a eunuch?
你现在没有手没有脚
You can work like anybody.
不能抬又不能挑吗？
Right?
是要服侍那马骝干嘛
Why bother that monkey of a man?
但是我割了
But I'm castrated.
我也可以说我割了小祖宗
I can say I'm castrated too.
你怎么知道我是不是呀，你说吧
Can you prove I'm not?
我屁股生疮，我屁股有两个洞
I can say anything.
有三个肚脐，谁知道呀？
Like I have 3 belly buttons, who can tell.
除了不可以生孩子外
As long as you keep your clothes on.
你又不脱裤子给人看
Who can tell the difference?
跟普通人有什么分别呀？
No eunuchs have been hired
不请太监很久了
for a while now.
除非有些太监老了、病了，就快断气
Unless the old ones are dying.
想赚取一笔棺材本
And need some money.
顶名费都要六十个钱，你有吗？
But then it costs 60 coins to fill in.
我…
But...
用心唱戏吧
你唱得好的话就有美好的前途了
Your future is here.
不要太多心了
Stop being silly.
师父    是了…
- Master - Alright...
我知道了…行了…
I know... Alright...
师父
Master.
师弟，去那里呀？
Where's the kid?
师弟，跟我们去喝花酒吧
Let's go to the girls.
师兄，我没有空，改天吧
I don't have time, may be next time.
师弟…
Hey, kid.
公公才不进入妓寨的，你是公公吗？
Only eunuchs are afraid to go in.
先检查一下
Let's check it out.
那个乱党走进了胭脂胡同，追他
The rebel gets lost in the whore houses.
追他，快点
Get him, hurry.
进去…
Go in, go in.
开门呀
Open up.
你很害怕？
Are you scared?
告诉你，等一会儿什么你也不会害怕
You won't be scared in a minute.
我没有钱的
I have no money.
已经付钱了
It's paid for.
来吧    不要
- Come on. - No.
你快点出来
Come out.
该死的
Damn.
捉到你就知道厉害
You will see when I get you.
没有声音的？
It's all quiet.
他们是你的朋友？
They are your friends?
谢谢
Thank you.
你为什么会做…
How come you...
做，做这种东西呢？
...you are in this business?
当初你有办法
It would have been different.
今日就不用被人家玩弄了
If you had your way.
我…
But...
真舒服
Feel good.
救命呀，苏姐，开门呀
Help! Soo, open up.
臭丫头，你还走？
Stop running, you trash.
开门呀，苏姐
Open up, Sister Soo.
开门呀，救命呀
Help, open up.
臭丫头，你快点出来，出来
Come out, you trash.
我不跟那个胖子睡，我宁死也不愿意
I'm not going to sleep with that fatso.
你不要害阿妈
Give your mum a break.
人家来了，钱又收了
He's here, and he has paid.
你现在叫我怎么办？
What am I going to do?
人是你叫来的，钱也是你收的
You asked him here, and he paid you.
要睡的话你跟他睡，我宁死也不愿意
You sleep with him.
你看看
I'll show you.
我今天一定要打死这个死丫头
You trash.
你说什么？
What did you say?
你不要过来    你说什么
- Don't come near. - What did you say?
那个肥佬给了多少钱开苞呀？
How much did that fatso pay?
这个小兄弟要顶了她
This kid will fill in for him.
苏姐，你不要跟我开玩笑
Don't kid me.
你看她的样子怎能见人呀
She's in no condition to work, look.
不如这样吧，我帮S顶了她
I'll fill in for her.
一毛钱也不少给你的
Not a penny less.
小弟弟，替我好好的照顾她
Take care of her, kid.
招弟？
Tsouti.
你不要过来
Don't come near.
招弟    不要过来
- Tsouti. - Don't come closer.
是我呀
It's me.
来喜呀
Laishi.
静海东柳木村那个来喜呀
The one from your village.
是你？
It's you?
你常常来找苏姐的？
Are you Soo's regular client?
不是，刚才外面捉革命党
我进来躲避一下
I slipped in among the rebels.
你是革命党    不是
- So you are a rebel. - No.
苏姐说革命党不会认自己是革命党的
All rebels deny they are.
苏姐又说革命党很风流的
Soo said all rebels are womanizers.
我不风流的
I'm not.
刚才是他们付钱捉我进来的
They pushed me in.
我连外面的浴室也不敢去
I wouldn't even go to the public bath.
我怕…
I'm afraid...
你以为你是女孩子吗？
You think you're a girl.
如果我是男孩子就好了
I wish I were a boy
我连名字也没有
and with a name.
你不是叫招弟的吗？
But your name is Tsouti.
招弟即是带一个弟弟来的意思
It only means
不是名字
to bring on a brother.
结果妈妈真的生了一个弟弟
A brother did come
说不够吃
and it became too crowded.
跟着把我卖到这里来
And my mum sold me to this place.
只得五个钱，比猪还要便宜
For five coins, cheaper than a pig.
为什么你走也不告诉我？
Why didn't you tell me?
你以为我不想找你吗？
I wanted to.
人家说你不知道割伤了那里
But they told me you were hurt
被妈妈困住了
and locked up.
你伤了的第二天
The next day.
我就被人捉到这里来了
I was sold to this place.
是呀，你割伤那里呀？
Yes, where did it hurt?
我…
I...
算了，你现在已经痊愈
Never mind, you are well now.
你不用替我难过
Don't feel sorry for me.
我当自己是只死猪，陪男人上床睡觉
I feel like a pig when I sleep with men.
是那些男人吃亏
It's their loss.
不要吧，我救你
Don't I'll rescue you.
我赚钱，我养你
I'll work and take care of you.
赎身要很多钱的
It costs a lot to buy me out.
我跟师父商量一下
I'll discuss it with my master.
不过这样子，这里那么危险
But you better.
你还是不要留在这里？
Not stay here.
你不用去问你老婆吗？
Don't you have to ask your wife?
我没有
I don't have one.
我什么也没有
I don't have anything.
我知道革命党是不会见死不救的
I know all rebels are courageous.
你走快两步，精乖一点
Hurry.
请你们快一点
Hurry up, please.
不知道，有的话我会告诉你
Don't know, I'll tell you when there is.
师兄，师父呢？
Where's the master?
我早说过不知道
I said I didn't know.
师兄，师父什么时候回来呀？
When will he be back?
真讨厌
What a drag.
师兄，你昨晚怎样搞掂苏姐的？
How's Soo, was she good last night?
她的外号叫一招了
They call her "One Stroke".
你怎样子跟那个处女开苞的？
And how's the virgin?
告诉我们    是
- Tell us. - Yes.
大师兄，麻烦你帮我去后门
Please see
看看有没有人找我
if someone's looking for me.
在这个时候，只有你才可以出去
Only you can go out and look.
他跛的吗？他自己不会进来吗？
Is he crippled, can't he come in himself?
是呀
Yeah.
她是个女孩子，这里怎可以进来呀？
She's a girl, she can't come in.
你好呀
Oh! Smart kid.
玉兰，有人找你
Yu Lan, someone's looking for you.
你们等一等
Please wait.
玉兰，他们说要找你
Yu Lan, they're looking for you.
你是不是刘玉兰？
Are you Liu Yu Lan?
是呀
Yes.
这位官大哥，我们的二老板不在？
Our boss isn't here.
是呀…
Yes...
不关你们二老板的事，也不关你的事
We are not here for your boss.
走开
Get away.
我们的雷大帅想请你喝酒
General Lei sends for you.
我今天没有空，改天吧
Some other time, can't make it today.
雷大帅在等你
General Lei is waiting.
我不认识他，麻烦你告诉他
I don't know him.
说我多谢了
Thank him for me.
是…
Yes, yes.
走
Let's go.
师父，喝茶
Tea, master.
你们算什么？
At least you can delay them
为什么不延迟到我回来？
till I come back.
他们有枪的
They have guns.
怕什么？他们有枪，我们没有刀呀
So you were afraid. We have sabers.
你们有意整蛊还是没胆子呀？
Was it a plot or you were scared?
在自己的地盘
Can't even protect.
自己的师兄弟也保不住了
A member of your troop.
怎能落班？怎能跑马头呀？
How can I depend on you in the future?
你鬼鬼祟祟的在干什么呀？
What are you doing here?
来喜在不在？你能不能带我去见他？
I'm looking for Laishi.
戏散了，所有的人都走光了
The show's over, nobody's around.
刘来喜，是他叫我来找他的
Laishi asked me to come.
别噜嗦了，叫她走吧
Send her away.
你让我看看他吧
Please take me to him.
谢谢你们，是他叫我来这里找他的
He asked me to come.
等一等…
Wait a minute.
你找来喜有什么事？我是他的师父
What do you want him for? I'm his teacher.
你是逃出来的吗？
Are you running away?
没事了，进去吧
Go back, it's alright.
你放心吧，来喜八岁就开始跟着我
Relax, I brought Laishi up with me.
我当是他爸爸一样
He treats me like his father.
来喜在不在？他叫我来找他的
Is he here? He asked me to come.
他出了事，被大帅带走了
He's in trouble. The general took him away.
是不是他的身份被人识破了？
Has he been discovered?
你知道他的身份？
You know everything.
在这里除了我一个人之外
I'm the only one
没有其他人知道
who knows.
其实他很凄凉
Poor kid.
平时连说一句话
He always keeps quiet.
也害怕人家识破他的身份
Has to be extra careful going to toilets.
甚至去厕所，大小便
Or change, or go take a bath.
脱衣服、洗澡，都特别小心
That gets him no friends.
所以弄到一个朋友也没有
That's why he denied it
难怪我猜中了他也不承认
when I made a guess.
原来你是靠猜的
You're only guessing?
那又不是，我跟他从小玩到大
Not really. I grew up with him.
后来失去联络，昨晚才遇上
And bumped into each other last night.
发觉他原来是…
And found out that?
虽然我怎样去问他，他也不肯承认
He denied it all along.
但是女孩子很敏感的
But call it a girl's intuition.
他叫你来干什么？
Why did he ask you here?
他叫我跟他一起生活
To live with him.
我考虑过了，他是一个好人
I've been thinking, he's a nice person.
我决定一辈子跟着他
I'll stay with him for life.
你想清楚呀，做夫妻不同做朋友
Are you sure that's more than being friends.
有很多事情夫妻一世流…
It is for life...
算了，我明白的
I understand.
有些事情我就当看不见
I'll cope with it.
他不肯说我就不问
I won't ask.
我可以替他保守秘密
I'll keep his secrets.
大家你迁就我，我迁就你
It's a matter of compromising.
一样会很开心的
We'll be happy.
来喜这只马骝仔真有福气
Luck little devil.
来喜是不是很危险呀？
Is he in danger?
恐怕不会死的，但是屁股可能会开花
Not too serious. It might hurt a bit.
刚才我在这里就好了
I wish I were here.
原来你和来喜都是…
You are both...
来喜是，我不是
Just Laishi, not me.
不是等于是，你们都不会承认的
You all deny it.
那我是了
So I am.
我已说过你们是的
See, I am right.
对…
Alright, alright.
停手
Stop.
别动
Don't move.
你们这些兔崽子想作反呀？
Are you crazy?
人家送来喜回来，就该客气一点
Be nice, they're Laishi's escorts.
我们有刀呀
We've got sabers.
刀？你妈的
So what? You stupid.
对不起，他们近来火气上升
Sorry, they're hot-tempered.
如果没事的话，不阻碍你们了
We won't delay you any longer.
二老板，雷大帅要我来通知你一声
General Lei sends a message.
什么呀？
What's that?
大帅很喜欢玉兰
He's going to marry Yu Lan.
明天会有大红花桥来接她过门
Tomorrow.
下聘礼
This is the wedding token.
你们回旅馆收拾东西
Go pack up.
然后来戏院找我
And see me later.
去吧
Go.
那禽兽有没有…
Did the beast?
没有    你的
- No. - Yours.
如果他明天抬花桥来的话，怎么办？
What if he sends for me tomorrow?
招弟在里面等着你
Tsouti's waiting for you inside.
明天早上城门一开，你就带她返乡下
Take her to your folks first thing tomorrow.
雷大帅就找不到你了
General Lei won't be able to find you.
师父，我这样子走了，会连累你的
But what about you, master?
难道你想跟雷大帅过着一辈子吗？
You want to live with Lei for life?
快点去吧
Go.
很难才找到像招弟逆来顺受的女孩子
Tsouti is a good girl.
不要婆婆妈妈了，女孩子不喜欢的
Don't act like a woman, she won't like it.
走吧
Go.
来吧
Go ahead.
怎么样呀？
How's it?
你那里开花呀？
Where does it hurt?
我…
I...
他们用火烧你？    不是
- They burned you with fire. - No.
用香烟烫你？    不是
- Burned you with cigarettes. - No.
夹你的手指？    不是
- Clamped your fingers. - No.
将你倒吊？    不是
- Hung you upside down. - No.
我不知道该怎样对你说
I don't know what to tell you.
当然是直接说
The truth of course.
难道还要音乐过场
Don't tell me.
让你慢慢唱出来吗？
You need violin music.
我…
I...
女人不喜欢什么呀？
What don't girls like?
快点说
Get it out.
我要去另一处地方，你跟我一起走吧
I'm leaving, I want you to come with me.
是不是特别任务？
Special mission.
不是
No.
军事秘密，不可以说出来的？
Military secret, can't you tell?
也不是
No.
我看你们怎样也不会说出来的
I know you won't tell.
你别胡思乱想了，返乡下耕田吧
Never mind, go back to the old home.
招弟很好的，她又可以替你守秘密
Tsouti is so nice. She'll keep the secret.
如果他欺负你，你告诉我
Tell me.
让我教训他
If he mistreats you.
师父，我们要走了，你要好好保重
Take care, master, we're going.
来喜，你忘了那个宝贝了
Laishi, you're forgotten your thing.
宝贝？
Thing?
有宝贝也不告诉我
Why didn't you mention this?
是什么？
What is it?
是他的小祖宗
That's his thing.
你不是革命党？
You're not a rebel.
我是公公
I'm a eunuch.
我不是想骗你的
I didn't mean to lie.
我是个乖儿子，又不风流，又不赌钱
I'm a good man, no fooling around, no gambling.
你又说不计较的
You'd said you didn't mind.
走开，你们两只怪物
Go away, you two freaks.
我？
I?
她不走，你自己走吧
She changes her mind. Go alone.
我是公公
I'm a eunuch.
我到那里人家也把我当怪物看待
I'll be treated as a freak.
你入宫吧，军阀不能进紫禁城拉人的
Go to the Palace. You're safe there.
在那里，就没有人把你当怪物看待
No one will treat you like a freak there.
但是你说过不要做太监的
But you told me not to go to the Palace.
没有，我没有说过
I didn't say that.
只要你挺着胸膛做人
Hold your head high
做一个硬桥硬马的太监
be a proud eunuch.
太监也是人
A eunuch has dignity too.
唱戏是骗饭吃，做太监也是骗饭吃
没有分别的
Just like being an actor.
跟公公请安
My respect to you, sir.
师父
Master.
站着，做个堂堂正正
Stand straight.
有骨气、有男子气慨的太监
Be proud, be a man.
是
Yes.
太监是这样说话的吗？
Is that how a eunuch would say it?
是
Yes.
用心干吧    是
- Be good. - Yes.
走吧
Go.
是
Yes.
弃我去者，昨日之日不可留
Yesterday has left me irretrievably.
乱我心者，今日之日多烦优
Today weighs me down with worries.
长风万里送秋雁
Send off those migratory birds.
对此可以酣高楼
And sleep off the day in style.
你是革命党？
You are a rebel?
那个乱党走了那里去？
Where's the rebel?
再到胭脂胡同里搜
So seraph the whore houses.
好像有人呀
Someone is there.
就是这个了
That's him.
顶包来的，小小意思
A fill in. Just a little gesture.
李爷，你漏掉了东西
You have left something.
走吧
Go.
叫他进来吧
Ask him to come in.
是
Yes.
进去吧，跪呀
Go in. Kneel down.
跪呀
Kneel down.
启禀丁公公，就是这个
This is the one, Lord Ting.
谢谢丁公公收留，丁公公福寿无疆
Long live Lord Ting.
叫什么名字呀？
What's your name?
小人姓刘，乡下的人叫我来喜
My name is Liu, they call me Laishi.
戏班师父叫我玉兰
My opera master calls me Yu Lan.
奴才该死
Forgive me, My lord.
你不是小人，你是奴才
You now call yourself a servant.
你不是来喜，你是春禄
You are no longer Laishi, you are Chun Lu.
公公知道你是冒充
His lordship knows you are a fill-in.
但是不喜欢亲口听你说，明白吗？
But he doesn't like to know it from you.
你究竟叫什么名字？
What's your name?
奴才…
Your servant...
奴才？
Your name.
春禄
Chun Lu.
验明正身没有？
Have you checked his purity?
是
Yes.
回公公，非常干净
Very clean, my lord.
好，春禄，宫中有很多礼法
Good, there is a lot to be learned.
譬如叩头请安、倒茶递水
All the rituals and procedures.
传话、回话，都有一定的规矩
All are governed by rules.
你多点向李爷学习，以后跟着李爷
Learn it from Lee, he'll teach you.
不要丢我的脸呀
Don't let me down.
是
Yes.
喳
老夫十三岁入宫
I came in at 13.
亲眼看见先帝登基大婚，变法维新
Have witnessed everything.
老佛爷两度垂帘听政
The Dowager's sovereign.
红毛鬼一把火烧毁圆明园
The burning of the Yuan Ming Yuan.
珍贵人跳井自尽，先帝驾崩
The murder of Lady Jane. The emperor's death.
到现在皇上说要大婚
Now the young emperor's wedding?
由一条开档裤到现在同皇后主子
A long journey of life.
同一个灶吃饭
都是先帝所赐，老夫无以为报
All under the grace of the late emperor.
只希望你们勤勤力力侍奉皇上
I only wish you would serve His Majesty well.
是
Yes.
奴才一定尽心服侍丁公公
I'll serve My lord with all my heart.
他日有机会服侍万岁爷
I'll do anything for His Majesty.
一定赴汤蹈火
皇上才是真命天子
His Majesty is the true leader.
我有机会一定效忠皇上
I'll be loyal to His Majesty.
报答皇上、服侍皇上
To pay back his generosity.
谢谢皇上恩典
Good.
好，小李，传话管事房
Give him some silver coins.
赐春禄白银二两
是
Yes.
以前老佛爷喜欢听戏
I learned singing.
我特意请你师父教我唱几句
With your master.
想不到一开腔老佛爷就死了
Before I could sing for the Dowager. She died.
你师父关照到我，我一定会照顾你我
I'll take care of you for your master.
要用心学呀
Learn well.
宝贝呢？
Where's your thing?
拿出来吧
Take it out.
李爷，他干什么？
What are they doing?
他们现在用石灰粉替你把宝贝腌了
To put it in calcium powder.
到你以后离开时候，就把宝贝还给你
It'll be returned to you when you leave.
跟我来
Follow me.
宝贝房？
The "thing" room?
是呀，我们每个人的宝贝
Everyone's thing is here.
都是放在这里的
That's mine.
那个就是我的
兄弟，很久没见，别来无恙吗？
Long time no see, brother. What's up?
放这么低，地气重，很容易会发霉
Lt'll catch the moisture down here.
你新来的
That's where you start.
以前李莲英那个就放在那里
The most honored one up there.
所以要勤力一点
One step at a time.
步步高升，就不会生虫了
Work hard.
是呀，是呀
Yes, yes.
这个是丁公公的
That's Lord Ting's.
用多点心思去学习吧
Work harder.
李爷，为什么要到玉泉山取水呀？
Why go to Jade Spring Hill for water?
皇上喜欢喝玉泉山的水没有苦涩味
His Majesty likes the water there.
又请不起苏拉，只有你和我去做
There's no other hands, just you and me.
给皇上喝，辛苦一点也是应该的
It's tough, but then it's for His Majesty.
不辛苦，是优差呀
It's not tough at all.
为什么？
Why?
取水嘛
You'll see.
春禄，你等我一会，我很快就回来
Wait for me, be right back.
李爷，用不用帮忙？
Can I help?
不用，在这里等我吧
No, wait here.
请
Please.
还有什么？
What else?
还有个钟
A clock.
究竟是不是宫中珍品？
Are those treasures from the Palace?
奴才该死，奴才不知宫中有什么珍品
Your servant wouldn't know.
李胖子有没有赏赐给你？
Has Lee given you money?
有，不过奴才没有要
Yes, but your servant refused.
起来    是
- Rise. - Yes.
大清有救了
There's hope for the Ching Dynasty.
春禄，我们不可以纵容这班败类
We can't let them go on.
是
Yes.
奴才从明天开始，不再替李爷送赃物
Your servant will stop smuggling treasures.
不可以，一定要送
No, you must go on.
你知不知道我准备找谁人呀？
You know who I'm going to see?
奴才不知道
Your servant wouldn't know.
你不要告诉别人
The master.
我找大总管商量商量
Don't tell anyone else.
到时你要做证人，我要人赃并获
You'll be witness. Catch them red-handed.
是，奴才一定会守秘密
Yes, at your service.
我很久没有听到人叫得这么正义凛然
Such refreshing words.
老佛爷有次游园赏花，赞我叫得响亮
The Dowager was once so pleased with my voice?
我毕生难忘
Unforgettable.
真是虎父无犬子
Like father like son.
再叫呀
One more time.
是
Yes.
好
Good.
是
Yes.
再多叫一次
One more time.
是
Yes.
走吧
Go.
有人偷运宝物，立刻搜查水车
Check the cart for smuggling.
是
Yes.
有没有发现？
Anything?
没有
No.
报告，没有发现
Nothing.
收队
Call if off.
你们走吧
Let's go.
等一等…
Wait.
宝物在这里呀
The goods are here.
是他偷出去卖的
He's responsible.
是，是他
Yes, it's him.
不错，是他，捉住他
Yes, get him.
是
Yes.
宝物是他偷的，不关我的事
He did it, I'm innocent.
我只是看见你一个人
I saw you only.
你等着去午门斩首吧
You're as good as dead.
抓他回去，快点
Take him back, quick.
冤枉呀，不关我的事
I'm innocent.
是他呀，冤枉呀
It's him, I'm innocent.
一、二、三、四、五
1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
六、七、八、九、十
6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
十一、十二、十三
11, 12, 13.
十四、十五、十六
14, 15, 16.
十七、十八、十九、二十
17, 18, 19, 20.
兄弟，可不可以拿杯水给我？
Buddy, can I have some water?
你还有知觉喝水？
Can you feel thirst?
如果不是皇上大婚，你早就被斩头了
You're a dead man but for the royal wedding.
求求你，我真的很口喝
Please, I'm so thirsty.
可以，先叫我做契爷
Alright, but call me sugar-daddy.
契爷
Sugar-daddy.
公公吉祥
Your lordship.
你们不要再耍我了
Don't play jokes on me, please.
奴才该死…
Your servant's at your mercy.
公公吉祥
Your lordship.
春福，你们俩去御茶房拿酸梅汤来
Chun Fu, get me some plum juice.
是
Yes.
敬事房、交泰殿、内左门、内右门
It is a conspiracy of the grandest scale.
干清门、御书房
十三宫的总管首领串同一起
Masters of 13 houses are all in it.
你是不是走黑运呀？
Tough luck for you.
是，奴才该死
Yes, "your servant" deserves it.
大清二百多年的国宝，古玩文物
The historical treasures of Ching.
竟然当废物论斤的卖给人家
Being sold like junk.
皇上被小人蒙蔽
His Majesty has been deceived.
如果这些事发生在十年前
If all this happened 10 years ago.
我要好好惩诫这班卖国贼
I would have them executed.
但是现在过了十年，那怎么办？
But this is not 10 years ago.
春禄，让你的伤好了之后
Chun Lu, when you are recovered.
我要你直谏皇上，你能做得到吗？
I want you to report it to His Majesty.
是，奴才做得到
Yes, your servant will do so.
好
Good.
我会替你好好安排…
I'll arrange it for you, I will.
大清有救了
There's hope for the Ching Dynasty.
奴才该死…
Your servant's at your mercy.
该死的不只你一个
Not just you.
娘娘贺寿，你安排的那出戏唱得真好
It was a good show.
叫什么呀？
For Her Highness's birthday.
八仙贺寿
That was "The 8 fairies' birthday gifts".
这是小人该做的事
Just part of my duty.
替主子安排玩乐是小人的责任
To entertain the masters.
对了，丁公公，你叫小人来
Oh, Lord Ting.
不知道有什么事呢？
Is there anything I can do for you?
没什么，我种了一盆未成器的盆栽
I have this budding plant.
请赵公公你过目，指点指点
Which I would like you to see and comment of.
不敢当，我是外行
I am no expert.
你是内行
You are so.
不，我是外行
No, I am not.
以后你就要多多关照了
Keep an eye on it then, please.
你太瞧得起我了
Very flattering.
你班奴才在这里干什么？
What are you doing?
还不快去做工
Go get some work done.
是
Yes.
你过来
Come over here.
丁公公吉祥，赵公公吉祥
Lord Ting, Lord Chao.
奴才以后也不敢那么放肆了
Your servant will be more disciplined.
这段贵妃醉酒的身段、神情都不错呀
That was a good "Drunken Empress".
他叫春禄
He is Chun Lu.
春禄    是
- Chun Lu. - Yes.
回赵公公话
Lord Chao wants to know
赵公公问你除了贵妃醉酒之外
your repertoire.
还会什么，告诉赵公公
Answer Lord Chao.
回赵公公，奴才还会三娘教子
Mother and Son, "The Bridge".
灞桥挑袍
The Robe.
玉堂春、宇宙锋、甘露寺
Spring Chamber, "The Temple".
不错
Not bad.
他懂得不少了    是呀
- That's quite impressive. - Yes.
真是英雄出少年
The young are getting better these days.
是呀
Yes.
怎么样？看得懂吗？
How about it? Do you understand?
奴才看不懂
Not really.
跟赵公公叫我明天去戏班练功
What has it to do with my rehearsal with Lord Chao?
有什么关S？
关S大了
A lot.
皇上每年新春，都去储秀宫听戏
His Majesty watches the opera each New Year.
你用心练习，让赵公公给一出戏你唱
Work hard.
到时…
And get to play a role, and?
来…
Come, come.
你在台上认真去唱，让皇上听得过瘾
Sing your best, when His Majesty is listening.
你不用理会打什么锣鼓
Then never mind the accompaniment.
不用理会赵公公打眼色打到发鸡盲
Or the conducting of Lord Chao.
你一口气念这一封万言书，直谏皇上
Recite this report to His Majesty.
是
Yes.
奴才就算推出午门斩首
I'll recede.
都要直奸皇上
Even if it costs my life.
不是奸，是谏
Not recede, it's recite.
是，直谏皇上
Yes, recite it.
好
Good.
公公，奴才觉得老百姓太多灾多难了
The people have been suffering for too long.
真命天子一定要重出江湖
The true emperor should make a come back.
斩奴党、杀军阀，复国安邦
And restore the country to its old glory.
好，你跟我念
Good, say it after me.
是
Yes.
亲爱的皇上
His Majesty dearest.
美丽底月亮已给漆黑底乌云盖上
The cloud hides the moon.
你一定没有听过五四运动
Haven't you heard of the 4th May Movement?
皇上现在流行时髦了
His majesty is very fashionable.
我读了一个月，看了很多新书才写成
I've spent a whole month writing this.
你的脑袋要革命了，做太监要新潮
You must follow the trend.
不然皇上听不入耳的
Or His Majesty won't like it.
我们继续吧
Let us go on.
是
Yes.
亲爱的皇上
His Majesty dearest.
美丽底月亮已给漆黑底乌云盖上
The cloud hides the moon.
蔚蓝的天空已给黑色的、乌鸦的
The ugly wings of a crow.
丑陋的翅膀掩蔽
Hide the blue sky.
蔚蓝的天空已给黑色的、乌鸦的
The ugly wings of a crow
丑陋的翅膀掩蔽
hide the blue sky.
多么可怕呀
So terrifying.
不得了啦…
Terrible news.
不得了…
什么事？
What is it?
启禀公公，建福宫大火的事
His Majesty is mad about the Palace fire.
皇上下诏赶我们出宫
He has given us one hour
限一个时辰内离开
to leave the Palace.
不然就处死
Or be executed.
不可能的，我要去见皇上
Impossible, I want to see His Majesty.
春禄，你还站在这里？
Don't just stand there, Chun Lu.
你还不去宝贝房，当心你的宝贝没了
Go get your "thing".
宝贝
Thing.
我的宝贝
My thing.
春禄？
Chun Lu?
我的宝贝呀
My thing.
我不离开这里
I don't want to go.
我离开了这里，能到哪里呀？
Where else can I go?
我不离开这里
I don't want to go.
人来，赶他走
Come, kick him out.
黄叔，你还不走？
Go, Wong.
走吧…
Go.
黄叔
Wong.
不要拖我走呀，我不离开这里
Don't drag me, I'm not leaving.
走，走呀
Go, go.
快点，走
Hurry.
报告长官，乱党全部都死了
Sir, all the rebels are dead.
收队    是
- March homeward. - Yes.
收队
March homeward.
先抬他的尸体回去吧，去吧
Collect the corpses first, go.
招弟？
Tsouti?
你在找亲人？
You looking for someone?
捉了个革命党
Caught another rebel.
又一个了
Another one.
走…
Go, go.
我知道你丈夫是革命党
I know your husband is a rebel.
大新闻…
Big news, big news.
满清最后一个皇帝被人赶出宫了
The last emperor is kicked out of the Palace.
大新闻…
Big news, big news.
满清最后一个皇帝被人赶出宫了
The last emperor is kicked out of the Palace.
妈疼你一下
Let mum kiss you.
这么早呀
So early.
我肚子很饿
I'm hungry.
今天生意很好
A good day today.
我把酸梅汤卖完了
Sold all the plum juice.
我一个钱也没有了
I don't have any money.
什么呀？你要钱干什么？
What do you need money for?
要…
Well?
要买东西送给你
To buy you something.
我储起来都是为了你
I saved it up for you.
将来不用摆档口，可以开间小店铺
To open up a shop in the future.
将来？将来是什么时候呀？
Future? When?
那就要看你勤不勤力了
It depends on how hard you'll work.
京生，吃不吃鸡腿呀？
Chinsheng, like the drum-stick?
老婆婆，你找谁呀？
What's up, granny?
你的眼看什么的？谁是老婆婆呀？
Granny? Are you blind?
我找春禄，春禄
I'm looking for Chun Lu. Chun Lu.
没有，没有春禄呀
No such person, no Chun Lu.
你知道谁是春禄吗？
You know who Chun Lu is?
京生乖    不知道
- Good boy, Chinsheng. - No.
怎么你又说没有
Then how could you say no Chun Lu here?
我要进去找他
I'm going in to look.
我已说过没有呀，走吧
I said no such person, go away.
不，我要进去
No, I'm going in.
丁公公吉祥
Bless you, Lord Ting.
够中气…
Such a voice, great.
起来…
Rise.
是
Yes.
丁公公，你出宫之后去了那里？
Where have you been, My lord?
西郊恩济庄
Out in the country.
我找得你很辛苦呀
I've been looking all over for you.
我都…
Me too...
奴才都是呀
Your servant has been doing so too.
你只是只顾自己，不用理我了
You only care about yourself.
果然干净
Still clear.
我还以为你那么棒有个儿子
I was wondering about the kid.
皇上现在被迫离开紫禁城
His Majesty is away from the Palace.
住在日本领事馆，很惨呀
Living in the Japanese Embassy, suffering.
春禄，我看我们要出动了
It's time for us to make a move.
春禄，你还记得吗？
Do you still remember?
记得什么？
What?
皇上对你恩重如山
That His majesty is your master.
现在皇上有难，你就沉迷美色
You have forsaken him for this woman.
奴才不敢
Your servant is guilty.
我记得…
I remember?
亲爱的皇上，美丽…
His majesty dearest, the cloud?
美丽底月亮已给漆黑底乌云盖上
The cloud hides the moon.
是，美丽底月亮…
Yes, the cloud hides the moon?
春禄
Chun Lu.
奴才该死
Your servant is guilty.
春禄
Chun Lu.
招弟
Tsouti.
我跟他多年的宾主关S
He's been my master for so many years.
我认是你的妹妹，又不是你老婆
I'm not your wife, more like a sister.
就算是的话也不管得那么多了
I have no right.
他来是聚旧的
He's here only for old times sake.
那你还留辫子干什么？
Why the pig-tail then?
我真的不争气
It's all my fault.
老佛爷，奴才对不起你
I have let you down, Your Majesty Dowager.
皇上有难，我只会敲经念佛
I could only pray when His Majesty was in trouble.
我没用
I'm so useless.
丁公公，你不要这个样子
Don't, My lord.
我没用，我连一个忠心报国的徒弟
I can't even keep a loyal servant.
也找不到
丁公公…
Lord Ting, Lord Ting.
我要一死以谢天下
I'll die to pay for my guilty.
丁公公，不要这样子
Don't, please.
你让我去死吧
Let me die.
你不要拉着我，你让我去死吧
Don't stop me, let me die.
我没用，你让我去死吧
I'm useless, let me die.
你让我去死吧
Le me die.
我要死，我不死也没有用
Let me die.
丁公公，不要这样子
Please don't be this way.
我要死…
I want to die.
不要呀
Stop that.
奴才该死
Your servant's at your mercy.
招弟，  你开门吧
Open up, Tsouti.
我不是回去做太监呀
I'm not becoming a eunuch again.
你开门吧，招弟…
Open up, Tsouti.
请公公见谅，奴才该死
Forgive me, My lord.
我不用人家可怜，我跳河死了算了
I need no sympathy, I'd rather die.
丁公公
Lord Ting.
没有了真命天子，中国何以为国？
Without an emperor, there is no empire.
我宁死也不做亡国奴
How can one be without a country?
无国又何以为家呢？
Without the county there is no home.
丁公公，你想我怎么样？
What do you want me to do?
你舍不舍得抛弃这个贱人？
Can you give her up?
不舍得的话就跟我滚回去
If not, get out of my sight.
舍得的话，明天就跟我去见皇上
If yes, we'll see the emperor tomorrow.
我肚子不饿，你先吃饭吧
I'm not hungry, you go ahead.
酸梅要干了水才可以踩呀
Let the plums dry first before squashing.
见皇上真的那么重要？
Is it so important to see the emperor?
丁公公说皇上有难
He's in trouble.
凭你们两个可以救皇上？
What can you two do?
丁公公说我们去服侍皇上
He said the emperor needs our services.
皇上需要我们
What about us?
皇上需要你，那我和京生怎么样呀？
你放心，我已经跟面店的张伯
I have talked to our clients.
家乡味的老黄
The noodle shops and the restaurants.
路口的张婶说好了
只要你每天送酸梅汤去就行了
Just deliver the plum juice to them.
你不要开档，太辛苦了
Never mind the cart.
是呀，记得酸梅要干了水才能踩呀
And let the plums dry before squashing.
记得酸梅干了水才能踩
Let the plums dry before squashing.
要放冰糖，不要加太多水
Use rock-sugar, not too much water.
够了，我要听的不是这些东西
Enough. I want to hear no more.
你说，是不是服侍皇上
Is the emperor more important than us?
比跟我们两母子一起好呀？
Don't forget you are just a eunuch?
一天到晚就皇上皇上
你不可以忘记自己是太…
是，我是
Yes, I am.
我是一个太监
I am a eunuch.
你知不知道我和你在一起的时候
When we are together
我就算被人家取笑，我都可以忍受
I can stand people laughing at me.
因为我已经习惯了
I'm used to it.
但是如果有人取笑你
But it hurts when they laugh at you.
我心里就很难过
Chinsheng needs a father.
京生需要爸爸
而皇上就需要太监
And His Majesty needs eunuchs.
所以…
That's why...
所以你就要跟丁公公走？
That's why you have to go.
难道你不想和我们好好的过日子吗？
Don't you want us to live happily together.
想，我不是不想
Of course, but...
狗仗人势的畜生
Your running dogs.
就是他们两个要见皇上
These two want to see His Majesty.
我们是专诚来侍候皇上的
请你让我们见皇上吧
Please let us.
你说要入就入的吗
See His Majesty.
你当这里是什么地方？
Where do you think.
叫他们走，不知所为
You are?
他说什么？
Send them away, such nonsense.
他说，这里不是皇宫，不用你们侍候
What did he say?
叫你们走
He said this was not a Palace, no need for you.
放肆
Told you to go away.
侍候皇上随便什么人都可以的吗？
Nonsense.
是呀，请你们让我们见皇上吧
His Majesty needs us.
如果他真的不需要我们
Yes, let us see him.
我们就走
If he really doesn't need us, we'll go.
走吧，也不知道现在是什么时代
Go, times have changed.
皇帝有我们来照顾
We'll take care of the emperor.
站着
Stand still.
什么？
What?
春禄
Chun Lu.
是
Yes.
验明净身
Check him out.
春禄，去吧
Chun Lu, go ahead.
是
Yes.
什么？你想干什么？
What are you doing?
这里是日本人的地方
This is Japanese property
不是每个中国人都能进来的
no Chinese allowed.
尤其是你这些奴才
Especially you, dummies.
走吧，奴才
Go away, dummies.
回公公，那个奴才很不干净
My lord, not clean at all.
赶他们走
Send them away.
赶我们？混帐
Nonsense.
皇上圣体，岂容你们左右侍奉？滚开
You have no right to serve His Majesty.
戆居
Ridiculous.
丁公公，我们先回去吧
Let's go back now.
不可以，我是总管，我要见皇上
No, I'm a master, I'll see the emperor.
公公
My lord.
我可以没了宝贝，不可以没了皇上
I'd give up my thing just to see His Majesty.
公公
My lord.
皇上英明…
Our glorious Emperor.
我们走
Let's go.
公公
My lord.
皇上吉祥
Long live the Emperor.
美丽底月亮已给黑漆底乌云盖上
The cloud hides the moon.
蔚蓝的天空已给黑色的
The ugly wings of a crow
乌鸦的、丑陋的翅膀掩蔽
cover the blue sky
多么可怕
So terrifying.
我现在将我的宝贝跟你一起埋葬
I'll bury the thing with you.
希望你有个全尸，来世可以投胎做人
So you can come back a complete man.
其实，一个真正的太监才要宝贝陪着
A real eunuch needs a thing.
我以后都不再做太监了
I'm a eunuch no more.
而且，割了下来的宝贝
What comes off
根本不属于任何人
doesn't belong anymore.
死兔崽子，一天到晚往外跑
You naughty thing.
你再不回家
Come home
我以后不理你了，知道吗？
or I'll lock you out.
不要哭了
Don't cry.
招弟
Tsouti.
我知道这次走了，令你伤心
I know I hurt you so much.
我很后悔这么糊涂，留下你们两个
I feel so regretful leaving you.
干出这么无谓的事
And did such a ridiculous thing.
本来我决定带同丁公公回来
I would have brought him home.
可惜他已经死掉了
But he's dead now.
我这次回来，不知你会不会原谅我？
Will you forgive me?
你不出声，是不是还在生我的气？
Are you still angry?
招弟
Tsouti.
既然你不肯原谅我，我走了
Maybe I'll go away.
你看看你，整个脸都是泥
Look at you, full of mud.
先洗脸吧
Go wash your face first.
谢谢
Thank you.
招弟  ，我…
Tsouti...
我想…
I want to...
你想怎么样？
What do you want?
我想你嫁给我，做我的老婆
I want to marry you.
你说什么？
What did you say?
我想你嫁给我，做我的老婆
I want to marry you.
你答应我吗？
Will you marry me?
你究竟答不答应我？你说吧
Will you marry me? Answer me please.
你不用说
Alright.
如果你答应我的话，你就不要踩
Stop squashing and it means yes.
如果你不答应我的话，那你继续踩吧
Carrying on means no.
你是不答应我的了
So the answer is no.
我什么也没有说过
I didn't say anything.
不过，这些酸梅汤明天要交给人家的
But we need to deliver tomorrow.
你答应我吧
Say yes please.
好吧
Yes.
你干什么？
What are you doing?
我已经下定决心了
I have made up my mind.
你这个样子就叫我嫁给你？难了
Look at you, how can I say yes?
我现在立刻出去把它剃掉
I'll cut it off.
交给你
For you.
我今晚顺便买些东西回来
I'll bring something back.
我们一家人开开心心庆祝一番
We three are going to celebrate.
等一等
Wait.
京生阿爹，外边冷呀，多穿件衣服吧
It's cold outside, Chinsheng's father.
京生阿爹？
Chinsheng's father.
我是京生阿爹？
I'm Chinsheng's father?
京生阿爹…
Chinsheng's father...
我是京生阿爹
I'm Chinsheng's father.
为什么单独坐在这里呀？
Why are you sitting there alone?
买给京生的，你看漂不漂亮？
For Chinsheng, isn't it pretty?
你不舒服吗？
Are you ill?
有人来了
Someone's here.
来喜
Laishi.
你好
How are you?
随便坐…
Make yourself at home.
瞧瞧你有客人来也不预早通知我
You should have told me earlier.
真对不起，我还没有…
I'm sorry, I am...
我还没有招呼你
I am not a very good host.
其实我家里也没有什么可以招呼的
We have not much to offer.
不如给碗酸梅汤你
Have a plum juice.
很好喝的，不会酸的
Good stuff.
你没有对他说我们的事吗？
Have you told him about us?
有
Yes.
为什么你现在才来找我？
Why do you come now?
不是现在，是从来也没有放弃过
I have never given up.
招弟
Tsouti.
你不是革命党？
You are a rebel?
我是
Yes, I am.
又说他死了？
You said he was dead.
来喜
Laishi.
汤倒泻了
The juice is spilled.
汤倒泻了可以再倒，但是…
It can be filled again, but...
你说得对
我不应该在这个时候回来找你们
I shouldn't have come at this time.
很多谢这两年来你照顾他们母子俩
Thank you for taking care of them.
这次回来能够再见他们
I'm too happy already.
我已经很开心了
To be able to see those two.
汉民
Hanming.
孩子，孩子乖
Good boy, good boy.
孩子乖，乖
招弟
Tsouti.
不要哭，乖
Don't cry.
来喜
Laishi.
我已经决定了，明天就走
I've made up my mind. I'll leave tomorrow.
要走的不只你一个，是你们
Not just you, but you two.
她常常跟我提起你
She always talks about you.
她也跟我说了很多关于你的事
I know a lot.
京生他…
Chinsheng, he...
你们也把他带走？
Take him with you...
是
Yes.
再见陈老师…
Goodbye Mr Chen.
快点回来呀…
Hurry back.
为什么来喜还不来送我们呢？
Why isn't Laishi here to see us off?
不知道会不会…
Could it be?
他不会的
He said.
他说要开档，开完档就来送我们
He would come.
而且他很胆心我们的安全
He's so worried about us too.
那最好了
Alright then.
买了，上车吧
Get on.
走开…
Get away.
大家醒醒吧…
Wake up, you, wake up.
打倒民国
Down with the Republic.
大清必胜，打倒民国
Ching will be restored.
大家醒醒
Wake up people.
走开
Get away.
皇帝万岁
Long live the Emperor.
谢谢
Thank you.
大清必胜，皇帝万岁
Ching will be restored, long live the Emperor.
发神经
Crazy.
我是皇帝的太监
I'm the emperor's eunuch.
皇帝很快就来这里，你们还不快回避
The emperor is arriving soon.
是不是想杀头？是不是想杀头？
Hide yourselves. Want to be dead?
你们这班贱民，以下犯上
是不是想死？
You low lives want to die.
想死？想死的是你，不是我
You are the one who should be dead.
太监？太你的头，瓣子也没有
Eunuch? Where's your pig-tail?
在这里发什么神经？
Such a ridiculous thing to say.
还不走就拉你去打靶
Go now, or we'll have you executed.
我真的是太监呀
I am a eunuch.
好
Alright.
你带几个人上车搜查
Search the coach.
跟我来
Follow me.
是
Yes.
站着
Stand still.
举起双手
Hands up.
走吧
Go.
别动
Don't move.
走吧
Go.
你，起来
You, stand up.
从那里来的？    山东
- Where are you from? - Shantung.
不用怕    山东？
- It's alright. - Shantung?
有没有带枪？
Carrying a pistol?
我不敢带枪
No, I dare not.
坐下
Sit down.
癫佬，你发神经呀
Are you crazy?
什么事？
What's up?
跟我来
Come with me.
来，你们来检验吧
Come, check it out.
验一验我是不是太监？
See if I'm really a eunuch?
谁说我不是太监？
Who says I'm not?
没有瓣子就是假的吗？
Even without a pig-tail.
没有下面是不是真的？
There's nothing down there, right?
来，你检验一下
Come check it out.
来，来检验一下，验一下
Come, come, check it out.
捉住他
Get him.
贱格
Scum.
装模作样
Fraud.
你没有的，还会痛吗？
How could that hurt, there's nothing there.
起来
Get up.
起来，打我吧
Get up and hit me.
废物
Trash.
贱格、下流、卑鄙
Scum.
走    是
- Go. - Yes.
夜已深深得似一张黑幕
Night, jet black night.
尽隔开欢笑留寂寞
Enveloping my solitude.
骤冷的空气冻结热情感觉
Chilling friendly feelings.
令我心跟冷风一样萧索
Making me shiver and shiver.
一生可得到几许欢乐
Life yields little mirth.
幸福只偶然拾获
Good fortune's a random harvest.
没法得到想要
What one wants is beyond reach.
得到不等于快乐
Fulfillment is not really happiness.
或许一切出于错觉
Excuse me if I am wrong.
或会将所想寻获
Perhaps there's light at the end of tunnel.
可惜我心思不再像旧时
My thinking has changed.
突破思想空壳我似骤然醒觉
It brings me face to face with reality.
或许一切出于错觉
Excuse me if I am wrong.
或会将所想寻获
Perhaps there's light at the end of tunnel.
可惜我心思不再像旧时
My thinking has changed.
突破思想空壳我似骤然醒觉
It brings me face to face with reality.
或许一切出于错觉
Excuse me if I am wrong.